Dr. Steven R. Goldman

Software Engineer II \cdot Space Telescope Science Institute 3700 San Martin Drive Baltimore, MD 21218 sgoldman@stsci.edu \cdot (667) 218-6542

Specialization: Evolved stars, dust, long period variables, symbiotic Miras, Magellanic Clouds, dwarf galaxies, Local Group, M31, UV to mid-IR imaging and spectroscopy, radio interferometry, spectral energy distribution (SED) fitting, time-series analysis, image alignment and drizzling.

Research Interests: The impact of evolved stars on their environment and vice-versa. Specifically, the effects of metallicity on the dust production, wind dynamics, mass-loss mechanism, and evolution of Asymptotic Giant Branch (AGB) stars and Red Supergiants (RSGs). This involves studies of statistical samples of nearby AGB populations using primarily the Hubble and Spitzer Space Telescopes.

APPOINTMENTS

Space Telescope Science Institute (STScI)

February 2023 - present

Baltimore, MD USA

Position: Science Software Engineer

Haverford College

January 2023 - May 2023

Haverford, PA USA

Position: Visiting Assistant Professor

Stratospheric Observatory For Infrared Astronomy (SOFIA) November 2021 - February 2023

Mountain View, CA USA

Position: Observatory & Instrument Scientist

STScI October 2017 - November 2021

Baltimore, MD USA

Position: Postdoctoral Fellow Supervisor: Martha Boyer

EDUCATION

Keele University

October 2013 - December 2017

Staffordshire, United Kingdom Degree: PhD in Astrophysics

Thesis: The metallicity dependence of maser emission and mass loss from RSG and AGB stars

Advisor: Jacco Th. van Loon

St. Lawrence University

September 2009 - July 2013

Canton, NY

Degree: B. S. in Physics

AWARDED PROPOSALS (PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR)

2022 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 17088 (\$137 k)	30 primary orbits
2022 SOFIA (first quintile)	18 hours (canceled)
2022 GASKAP-OH (Science team lead: LMC maser populations)	50 hours
2021 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 16492 (\$65 k)	4 primary orbits
2021 SOFIA, PID: 75_0057 (\$40 k)	4 hours
2017 Australia Telescope Compact Array Telescope, PID: C2996	92 hours

2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 099.D-0907	1 Night
2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 098.D-0272	0.5 hours
2016 Very Large Telescope XSHOOTER, PID: 097.D-0605	1.5 hours
2015 Westerbork Synthesis Radio Telescope, PID: R14/010	30 hours
2014 Southern African Large Telescope	5.5 hours
2012 National Science Foundation Summer REU Fellowship	

RECENT AWARDED PROPOSALS (CO-INVESTIGATOR)

James Webb Space Telescope (3 programs)	72 primary / 2 parallel hours
Hubble Space Telescope (9 programs)	120 primary / 535 parallel orbits
SOFIA (2 programs)	20.25 hours
SOFIA Legacy (cut short by cancellation)	100 hours \rightarrow 4 hours
ACA (NESS)	750 hours
Astrophysics Data Analysis Program (18-ADAP18	8-142) \$335 k
ALMA	5 hours

SELECTED SEMINAR & CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2024 Talk, AAS Winter Meeting	New Orleans, USA
2022 Invited Speaker, IAU General Assembly	Busan, South Korea
2022 Featured Speaker, AstroPhilly22	Villanova University, USA
2022 Invited Colloquium	University of Auckland, New Zealand
2022 Invited Colloquium	University of Canterbury, New Zealand
2022 Invited Talk, AAS Summer Meeting	Pasadena, USA
2022 Invited Colloquium	NRC Herzberg, Canada
2021 Invited Panelist, Evolved Stars and their Circumstella	ar Environments Global (Remote)
2021 Invited Talk, GAPS: unsolved problems in red Giants	s And suPergiantS Global (Remote)
2021 Talk, DELVE: The Death-Throes of Evolved Stars	Global (Remote)
2021 Invited Talk	St. Lawrence University, USA
2020 Invited Talk	STScI, USA
2019 Invited Colloquium	RIT, USA
2019 Invited Colloquium	EAO Hawaii, USA
2019 Talk, A Star Has Evolved: A Conference in the Hono	9 ,
2019 Talk, HotSci	STScI, USA
2018 Talk, Cosmic Dust: origin, applications & implication	• • •
2018 Talk, European Week in Astronomy and Space Science	- · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·
2016 Talk, Blowing in the wind (Awarded Best Talk)	ICISE, Vietnam
2016 Talk, Postgraduate Research Symposium (Awarded E	•
2016 Talk, SKA Delivering the Science	Cambridge University, UK
2015 Talk, UK SKA Science Meeting	Manchester University, UK
2015 Invited Colloquium,	Kagoshima University, Japan

TEACHING

Haverford College, USA Astro 101, Visiting Assistant Professor	Spring, 2023
Keele University, UK	
Electronics, Demonstrator/Lab Assistant	2014-2016
Programming I, Demonstrator/Lab Assistant	2015

STUDENTS MENTORED

Tessa Pearlstein Haverford College, Summer 2023

Dust Injection Rate of TP-AGB stars in the M33 galaxy

Sean Garner SOFIA/USRA, Summer 2022

SOFIA/EXES Water Line Analysis of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge

Nathan Wolthuis SOFIA/USRA, Summer 2022

HST/WFC3 Image Analysis of Nebular NII emission of HM Sqe

OBSERVING EXPERIENCE

SOFIA	3 flights
James Clerk Maxwell Telescope	70 hours
Very Large Telescope	1 night
Australia Telescope Compact Array	92 hours
Parkes Radio Telescope	36 hours
Arecibo L-band (ALFALFA)	20 hours

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT ()

Observatory Service

- *Drizzlepac*: Primary maintainer for the widely-used image re-alignment software also used for the alignment, drizzling, and catalog creation for the Hubble Advanced Products.
- SOFIA Data-Analysis Cookbooks and FAQs: Jupyter notebooks demonstrating a variety of techniques for analyzing infrared data from SOFIA, as well as detailed explanations FAQs of common misconceptions.

Research

- \circ The *DESK*: Independently led the development and publication of the first open-source python package to fit the SEDs of evolved stars with models to get meaningful intrinsic properties.
- The BEAST: Improved on testing and functionality of a large-scale open-source astropy-affiliated python package that fits stellar populations' SEDs to determine ISM, dust, and stellar properties using Bayesian statistics, dust models, and stellar evolutionary models.

COMMUNITY OUTREACH

Public Outreach Talks, 2018-Present, (USA, Canada, & Mexico)

o NASA's Universe of Learning, Skype-a-Scientist, Astronomy On Tap, Independently organized

Earth and Space Observatory volunteer, 2013–2017, (Keele University, UK)

ACADEMIC SERVICE

Organized the SOFIA New Zealand Lecture Series

SOFIA School Co-Chair

STScI postdoctoral representative

DELVE conference SOC

Low-Density Universe Lunch Organizer

July 2022

February 2022

February 2021

2018 - 2019

TAC Panel Support: Hubble & SOFIA

Referee: Astrophysical Journal; Astronomy & Astrophysics

SELECTED PRESS

NASA press release, NASA's Hubble Finds Surprises Around a Star That Erupted 40 Years	(Link)
Phys.org, Research investigates evolution of symbiotic binary HM Sagittae	(Link)
Sky at Night magazine interview about SOFIA New Zealand deployment	(Link)
NASA press release, SOFIA Watches a Binary Star System's Eclipse	(Link)

Links: ADS, ORCID, Google Scholar

Citations source: NASA ADS

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

First-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- Goldman S. R. et al., 2024, ApJ, 961, 14
 A Multi-Wavelength Study of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge with SOFIA & HST
- 2. Goldman S. R. et al., 2022, ApJS, 259, 41 citations: 6
 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 3. Goldman S. R., 2020, JOSS, 5(54), 2554 citations: 7 The Dusty Evolved Star Kit (DESK): A Python package for fitting the Spectral Energy Distribution of Evolved Stars. Journal of Open Source Software
- 4. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 884, 152 AGB Stars in the Nearby Galaxy: Leo P
- 5. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 49 citations: 33
 An Infrared Census Of Dust In Nearby Galaxies With Spitzer (DUSTiNGS): V. The Period-luminosity Relation For Dusty Metal-poor AGB Stars
- 6. Goldman S. R. et al., 2018, MNRAS, 473, 3835 citations: 15 A dearth of OH/IR stars in the Small Magellanic Cloud
- 7. Goldman S. R. et al., 2017, MNRAS, 465, 403 citations: 126 The wind speeds, dust content, and mass-loss rates of evolved AGB and RSG stars at varying metallicity

Co-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- 8. Karnath et al. 2024, accepted in ApJ An Analysis of the Complex and Compact Outflow Cavity Carved by HOPS 361-A in NGC 2071 IR
- Gull et al. 2022, ApJ, 941, 206
 A Panchromatic Study of Massive Stars in the Extremely Metal-Poor Local Group Dwarf Galaxy Leo A
- Ingallinera et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 21
 Evolutionary map of the Universe (EMU): 18-cm OH-maser discovery in ASKAP continuum images of the SCORPIO field
- 11. Sankrit et al. 2022, ApJ, 926, 177 SOFIA/FORCAST Monitoring of the Dust Emission from R Aqr: Start of the Eclipse

- 12. Scicluna et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 1091
 - The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey II: Constructing a volume-limited sample and first results from the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope
- 13. Jones et al., 2021, MNRAS, 504, 565
 Infrared variable stars in the compact elliptical galaxy M32
- 14. Girardi et al., 2020, ApJ, 901, 19
 PHAT XX. AGB stars and other cool giants in M31 star clusters
- 15. Nanni A. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 487, 502

 The mass-loss, expansion velocities and dust production rates of carbon stars in the Magellanic Clouds
- Dharmawardena T. E. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 489, 3218
 The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey: I. JCMT/SCUBA-2 Sub-millimetre detection of the detached shell of U Antliae
- 17. Karambelkar V. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 110 SPIRITS Catalog of Infrared Variables: Identification of Extremely Luminous Long Period Variables
- 18. Orosz G. et al., 2017, AJ, 153, 1190 Astrometry of OH/IR stars using 1612 MHz hydroxyl masers. I. Annual parallaxes of WX Psc and OH138.0+7.2
- 19. Groenewegen M. A. T. et al., 2016, A&A, 596, A50
 The ALMA detection of CO rotational line emission in AGB stars in the Large Magellanic Cloud
- 20. McDonald I. et al., 2015, MNRAS, 453, 4324 ALMA reveals sunburn: CO dissociation around AGB stars in the globular cluster 47 Tucanae

Other Publications:

- 21. Goldman et al. 2022, Research Notes of the AAS, 6, 159 Sudden Dimming of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge
- 22. Goldman et al. 2022, AAS Meeting, 240 proceedings, 426.04
 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 23. Sloan et al. 2021, AAS Meeting, 237 proceedings, 541.16 Spitzer's Last Look at the Small Magellanic Cloud.
- 24. Scicluna et al. 2020, arXiv:2002.03100 (Decadal white paper)
 Studies of Evolved Stars in the Next Decade: EAO Submillimetre Futures White Paper Series
- 25. Karambelkar et al. 2020, , AAS Meeting, 235 proceedings, 335.04 SPIRITS catalog of infrared variables : Identification of extremely luminous long period variables
- 26. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, IAU Meeting 343 proceedings, 14(S343), 406-408 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars
- 27. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, AAS Meeting 233 proceedings, 33.06 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars